foreign
2023 we're here in active bookstream
number 1.09
off to you blue
hi I'm blue Knight I am a researcher in
New Mexico and we are the active and
Friends Institute of participatory
online Institute that is communicating
learning and practicing applied active
inference you can reach us at our social
media links here and um just a reminder
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve on our
work all backgrounds and perspectives
are welcome here and we will be
following good video etiquette for live
streams and just as we're mentioning
that all backgrounds and perspectives
are welcome here we will be having our
final discussion coming up in about four
weeks so if you would really like to
participate if you've watched some of
the live streams and have some questions
we would really like to get some outside
perspective so please get in touch with
us so that you can participate in our
final discussion
um so like I said if you want to
participate this is how uh and so we are
still discussing governing continuous
transformation
um and today our goal is to discuss
section nine so chapter nine um and we
will be doing book map road map and all
of the typical things so I already
introduced myself
um Daniel just gave us the date why
don't you introduce yourself
it's Daniel in California I'll pass to
Tyler
uh I'm Tyler in California I am a uh Dao
researcher and protocol designer
all right blue
all right so here we are at the end of
part two so next week uh the author is
going to join us for a discussion over
part two the free energy governance
section of the book and then we'll be
moving into part three I think we're
gonna do two chapters at a time as we go
through part three and I don't think
we'll be discussing the engaged
scholarship interviews but if you're
curious about them I encourage you to
read the text
okay uh Tyler do you want to read this
first part of the abstract for us sure
all right so beneath all chaos is an
underlying structure a challenge is to
exploit disorders underlying order
survive living organisms are encoded to
resist disorder I.E entropy by way of
self-organization firms are nothing more
than molecules and are subject to
obeying the very same laws
thermodynamics entropy will eventually
rise three specific propositions
previously developed as part of this
book's underlying dissertational
research are outlined one structure the
stronger affirms cross hierarchical top
down bottom-up cognitive throughput
coupling between and within governance
and operational channels the less
dominant firm's top-down approach
cultivating a form of CEO centrism and
strategy ownership
all right blue you want to take the next
next one
yes
so two cognition the stronger affirms
cognitive disposition toward
environmental enactment and Innovative
abduction as opposed to adaptation the
stronger the firm's strategic control
and the smaller the risk of falling for
the financial control trap three
capabilities the stronger the board's
dmn Centric Duality stewardship
empowering upper echelon to sustainably
balance exploitation versus exploration
as well as Financial versus strategic
control the stronger the sustainability
of successful and continuous strategic
renewal and hence the firm's prospects
for survival
strategy is less macroscopic but more
subatomic less linear and deterministic
but more Quantum and discontinuous there
is a dominant tendency of glorifying the
realest beauty of top-down linear cause
effect relationships to the very
detriment of quantum self-organization
and I'm going to start off just reading
this
um
heart from the book so Bijan says I'm
trying to see it over my screen order
anywhere in the cosmos is so singular it
always requires an exemplary mechanism
or process while randomization requires
no
I can't read the word it is simply The
Way of the World when particles are
allowed to act randomly whether it's the
contents of a glass on of club soda on
the rocks or the countless atoms making
up the air in the room they slam into
each other exchanging energy into
complete randomizations of their
positions and velocities is observed and
so Bajan quotes
um this lonza at Al 2020 paper and I was
just like thinking of like firms as like
organized organizations of people and
like it really brought this picture to
mind of like you know Adam's randomly
slamming into each other like people
randomly like slamming into each other
like the mosh pit versus like the board
meeting
I just wanted to bring this like a
juxtaposition of like like what is it to
like minimize free energy in terms of
like assembling humans as opposed to
like assembling atoms anyway I just had
to share with this like mental image
um okay
Tyler do you want to read this one for
us sure all right so beneath all chaos
is an underlying structure our challenge
is to exploit disorders underlying order
to survive living organisms are encoded
to resist disorder or 90 entropy by way
of self-organization firms are nothing
more than molecules and are subject to
being the very same laws thermodynamics
uh and so yeah I thought this was I
thought the connection here that was
interesting was comparing uh
saying that the laws of thermodynamics
apply to firms and that's what's really
going on and we've talked about this in
previous streams I know we have uh Blues
kind of talk about a little more in
detail here about whether that's more of
like an analogy comparing to
thermodynamics or something like a real
underlying structure of thermodynamics
and we'll talk about that more shortly
that also brings to mind like the mosh
pit like and like I wonder in our base
case as humans like are we like just
chaotic like is our natural inclination
to be like increasingly chaotic and like
we override that
um it just I don't know I I had all
these mental images as I was reading
this as well so
um oh yeah Tyler uh put this in so I
love this um I'm gonna read it because I
love it
uh so Vision says
oh he actually quotes Gould at Owl 2016.
so
um and in the quote he says if physical
theories were people thermodynamics
would be the village witch over the
course of three centuries she smiled
quietly as other theories Rose and
withered surviving major Revolutions in
physics like the Advent of General
relative relativity and quantum
mechanics the other theories find her
somewhat odd somehow different in nature
from the rest yet everyone comes to her
for advice and no one dares to
contradict her Einstein for instance
called her the only physical theory of
universal content which I am convinced
that within the flame framework of
applicability of its basic concepts will
never be overthrown her power and
resilience lay mostly on her Frank
intentions thermodynamics has never
claimed to be a means to understand the
mysteries of the natural worlds but
rather pass toward a efficient
exploitation of said World
um yeah do you want to add comments here
Tyler
yeah I mean I liked about this was that
like
the kind of like mystical business
leader like a Steve Jobs character is
kind of like a Trope in the business
world and it's kind of like almost like
a joke at this point but there's also
like a real case for the mystical
business leader which is almost kind of
what I think the John is like describing
here is that you know the real state of
the world of like operating
um as a firm in a very uncertain
uncertain is probably not the word I
should use but like inactive in an
active sense like is a very mystical
receptive way of engaging with the world
um and I really like making that
connection of mysticism with like
business with like you know corporations
one other angle there is organizations
are doing work they're doing hopefully
useful work and thermodynamics is
concerned with how thermal energy that
uncorrelated exchangeable entropic
dissipation can be channeled into moving
the steamboat forward or lifting up the
weight on the crane and so sometimes
with the amount of seething activity in
formal firms or informal groups it's
like but if we all just went in this
exact Direction at this exact time
we could do this it's like well if all
the air molecules just slammed against
the wall it would fall over or if they
all formed into uh a droplet you'd get
rain in the room like thermodynamics
helps us understand
what is likely to happen
given those interacting State spaces and
again interestingly it has to do with
extracting work useful work from this
background of just vibration that's not
work
yeah
yeah and so the other thing I like too
just to build on that is that like it's
okay to not know what's going on is that
like that doesn't necessarily need to be
a source of stress it's just like you
can harness those energies and kind of
see which way the wind is blowing so to
speak without necessarily understanding
understanding all the underlying
principles I'm like that's totally okay
and I think that's generally something
that gives a lot of people both in the
business world and even in our personal
lives a lot of stress but this is also I
think a very like freeing way to
approach uh an uncertain and uncertain
world
foreign
yeah and and there's also like
um just come maybe to close the loop or
maybe open it up a little bit more
um there's also the prospect of doing
work that you don't know is going to be
fruitful right and so like that is this
like uncertainty minimization like you
could spend you know your whole like an
hour trying to crack open a nut and the
nut is empty like like that's also
possible right so like doing even though
you're doing work like that's maybe
useful work
um it might not bear fruit so there's
there's that like uncertainty element
like as just a human or also like as a
firm
um
so I just wanted to bring back these
slides like while we're talking about
thermodynamics we talked about this a
long time ago and we talked about the
difference between like thermodynamic
entropy and information theoretic
entropy
um and so I just wanted to kind of bring
this back and just remind everyone that
um there's a difference uh there is
relationships between the two that are
still being hashed out like
mathematically
um and and not totally understood but
but the second law of Thermodynamics is
that this entropy like disorder in the
universe is always increasing
um and like here like the you know the
energy is always lost in a transfer in
in work as heat to the environment in
yeah so
less and less usable energy becomes
available all right
um and then in information Theory we
kind of talked about entropy as like
with an inverse relationship with
um
information so here you can see like a
event that is
low probability is high information so
like if you're decoding a stream of
letters I always like to think about it
like this because it was explained to me
like that and it made so much sense if
you're decoding a stream of letters and
and like you're expecting a message and
this was Claude Shannon
um and kind of like how he or how it was
explained to me how how he kind of came
up with this so you're decoding a
message and you get the letters t h it
would be really freaking weird if like
the next letter was Z like I don't know
any words that have THC like that's a
very low probability event right so so
it would be like a very high information
thing or like you know maybe something
came before the th and you missed it but
there's some probability like t-h-e
would be great or like t-h-i but like th
Z wouldn't make any sense unless like
the th was at the end of some previous
word and so like you can kind of deduce
what to expect in those kinds of
situations
um and so yeah the um probability
distribution is like when there's 50 50
probability so so this is the second
graph on the right when there's 50 50
probability like the flip of a fair coin
that's super high entropy like you don't
have any idea if it's going to be heads
or if it's going to be Tails
um but like it here it's low entropy if
it's like a coin with two heads there's
heads on both sides like you can only
come out with heads so like there's very
low entropy and such a coin flip because
the outcome is always heads
um right if there's no distinction
between the two sides so I don't know
that's the thermodynamic entropy versus
information theoretic entropy and I
think we
talk a lot about thermodynamic entropy
but maybe forget that the fep is really
kind of
founded in the information theoretic
entropy as well
um do you guys have anything to add here
no okay
um all right so Bhajan makes this claim
in this section and I'm not going to
read the claim but I'm just going to
point out that here we kind of have a
really concise definition of like he's
been emphasizing the structure cognition
and capabilities for a few chapters now
and so here he defines structure as the
the circular coupling circular coupling
of governance predictions and
operational stimuli channels in the form
of prediction error minimization he
defines cognition as environmental
engagement in the form of enactment
rather than adaptation and he defines
capabilities as sensing and sense making
in the form of Duality management and so
this chapter was really kind of a good
um like summary chapter I thought I can
and kind of gives us a chance to go back
and revisit like a couple of the
concepts that that we talked about
before but maybe need to highlight one
more time
um
do you want to read this one Tyler Frost
sure so yeah through the rest of the the
chapter John is going through each
treasure of cognition
um and he's really kind of going deep
and kind of recapping what he's been
covering through the previous the rest
of the book uh so for structure he says
the stronger affirms cross hierarchical
top down bottom-up cognitive throughput
coupling between and within governance
and operational channels the stronger
the firm's orientation towards free
energy surprise minimization based on
self-organization the less dominant
affirm's top-down approach cultivating a
form of CEO centrism and strategy
ownership the stronger sustainability of
successful and continuous strategic
renewal and hence the firm's prospects
for survival
cool thanks
um and so this is kind of like the the
punchline of the structure and so I
pulled out maybe just a couple topics
from
um from before the punch line uh to talk
about
um and so this kind of like top-down
bottom-up coupling I was like looking
for a picture of like what just top down
bottom-up coupling like look like like
how do you
see that can I visualize that actually I
was like looking for a picture to put on
the previous slide and I came across
this like 2008 paper from emotion
residence to empathic understanding a
social developmental Neuroscience
account and like my background is
neuroscience but it's definitely like
cellular and molecular Neuroscience so I
don't really have a good like
comprehensive reading of of Social and
developmental like neuroscience and what
that looks like and I was like I loved
this figure because it just was so
like encompassing of so many of the
things that um we've talked about so far
Daniel have you read this paper have you
ever seen this before like I hadn't
either and I came across the figure and
I was like oh I have to get the paper
now
um and so it was nice to kind of just
delve into this and it's really about
um what's required for empathy
um but I just is so and I'll talk more
about it but here you see like the top
down bottom up coupling
um so it's bottom-up information
processing top-down information
processing relation to like with really
relative to the individual and then the
context or situation
um and and there's this perception
action coupling and then like 2008 I'm
like the perception action loop from
2008 this is cool
um and and they talk about shared
representation
um and this like self other awareness
which we talked about a couple book
streams ago like um how like
distinguishing the the self versus The
Other Self and non-self
um so I thought that this was really and
executive functions regulation and
control metacognition like the looking
at um like that's like double Loop
learning the the metacognition aspect so
I thought that this paper was really
cool and and
um it really was like wow all of this is
is like grounded in empathy
um anyway it was me it was a good read
uh it's Destiny and Meyer of 2008 and
the link is up there if you want the DOI
or any of that stuff um and it made me
think like all this is grounded in
empathy so like what is like we know
like or at least it's thought in
business that like to be successful as a
business person your emotional potion
your EQ is like way more important than
your IQ like your ability to relate to
others and interact with people so like
a good emotional High emotional quotient
versus like an intelligence quotient is
way more crucial to
um business success and so I just wonder
about like the relationship between if
any between free energy governance and
like the emotional quotient like is
there like I like John never talked
about this directly in the book but it
just made me think like how important is
empathy for this kind of governance
structure
um I don't know if you guys have any
thoughts here on this
yeah I mean I think empathy is just
really like sensitivity to your
environment or sensitivity to like other
actors and their internal States and so
in the context of a firm like it doesn't
necessarily need to be like their emote
the
you could think of an emotion
necessarily as like for a another firm
uh maybe the internal state of this
external other firm so maybe like you
are dependent on this other firm things
aren't kind of going the way you would
expect them to go with this other firm
maybe orders or a backlog or their API
is being kind of intermittently down
maybe that is like a signal into the
internal state of that firm and the
internal state of the ecosystem as well
and so I think that that might be like
analogous to an emotion in a human
context Maybe
they had a bunch of definitions actually
in the paper and I can't pull it up
because I'm I'm screencasting so I'm not
going to let you guys like go through my
go through all my 25 000 open windows
but maybe we'll pull them out um and and
this is like maybe a good question for
Bhajan about the relationship between
empathy and the free energy governance
when we get to see him next week but
they had like several different
definitions of empathy too in the paper
which I thought was interesting they
really really tried to take like a very
like logical approach to it and it's
cool
um okay so here is a claim from the
paper Bhajan says the higher the
organizational friction in terms of
obstructing bottom-up error messages
traveling to and reaching top-down
prediction generators the higher free
energy the potential for surprise and
the more likely that top-down dominant
Logics fossilized prediction models and
hence reinforce a firm's entropy
um and like this is something that maybe
Tyler and I have brought up either on
stream but we've talked about it off
stream a lot like how do we reduce this
organizational friction like where are
the um
examples to that show us like what is
the best way to like reduce this
friction to like create a good top-down
bottom-up coupling like we know that
this coupling is super important like it
all layers across the hierarchy but like
can we find like an empirical
way like that works in all situations to
build that that structure
um and that that I think is like a
challenge or maybe a future research
question
I guess another thing that is a little
counterintuitive about this too is that
oftentimes the things that will reduce
friction and maybe like the longer term
feel high friction in that moment so for
example like in previous streams we've
been talking about like dissonance as
being like a way of thinking about that
friction right well the easiest way to
deal with dissonance the lowest
frictional way you could deal with it
personally is just like not thinking
about it and just like tunnel vision and
just like ignore it and don't worry
about these weird feelings that you have
um and that but that obviously doesn't
help the version of the organization as
a whole
um and so yeah there's this kind of
especially in your personal life too by
analogy is like confronting your own
emotions that you don't want to think
about in the short term really easy to
just like power through and just keep
doing what you're doing but if you can
like process these and integrate these
emotions
um that's a lot healthier for you long
term so it's an interesting kind of like
tension between like your individual
Tendencies of like not winning friction
and like friction in the organization as
a whole
also to connect back to the
thermodynamics what is friction well
it's when a force is applied on some
surface
or through some media and it results in
heat which is dissipated taking away
energy from what could have been done
for work and now think about friction
engineering do we coat every object with
Teflon do we want everything to just at
the lightest touch fly off into space so
just because we can increase or reduce
friction actually doesn't tell us
especially over time scales like you're
bringing up Tyler
whether we want something to have a lot
of friction like where the rubber hits
the road or whether there are some
fundamental trade-offs with how much
heat the tire is losing in contact
with a smooth Road versus how much grip
it has on a loose Road and so all these
different trade-offs are where the
actual Art and Science is going to come
into play but friction is not just a
term that's used every day to describe
annoying communication patterns FEG is
pointing towards that potentially being
understood as an actual physical Force
cool uh do you want to read this one for
us Tyler
sure so the second proposition in
cognition so the stronger affirms
cognitive disposition towards
environmental enactment and Innovative
abduction as opposed to adaptation the
stronger the firm's orientation towards
free energy surprise minimization based
self-organization the stronger the firm
strategic control and the smaller the
risk of falling for the financial
control trap the stronger the
sustainability of successful and
continuous strategic renewal and hence
the firm's prospects for survival
yeah
all right and so I I I'm gonna read
another quote from this section on
cognition
um and I brought back this picture
because I think it's important um okay
so Bijan says cognition in the form of
world enactment is the purpose-directed
action-centric and social construction
of shared meaning and shared
expectations anchored in the
understanding that a firm's environment
is a matter of environmental engagement
in the form of interaction revealing
significance and assigning probabilities
to a bounded set of external unknown
States and so like I'm coming back to
this paper and I'm looking at like the
information processing bottom up top
down and like here I see this like
shared representations and we've seen
this like in like in this figure in this
paper they're talking about like body
language and like somatic response like
heart rate increase or lower and all
these things that have been measured in
like the generation of empathy but like
is is empathy maybe something that is
required for shared meaning or shared
expectation like I I wonder is like do
you have to
have that like like it is a sociopath
like devoid of empathy empathy like
living in a world where like things
don't mean the same thing and
expectations aren't the same like maybe
right like there might be a a strong
link there that I wonder if it's been
explored or not so I'm just curious if
you guys have
thoughts on what developing shared
meaning and expectation is and if it
requires some kind of empathy with
others
yeah I I share that feeling one of the
big questions I've had through this and
honestly it's on a personal level I've
always been interested on like whether
you can build tooling that would help
create that shared meaning and
expectations uh or whether this is
really just constrained by like the
individual like if you're if you have
people who are sociopaths in your
organization
um maybe it's just like there's certain
the way that they're wired it kind of
limits the way that they can engage and
create shared meaning with the rest of
the organization and so yeah I'm kind of
curious what you all think about that
too like I don't have an answer for it
but then maybe that'd be a good question
for Sean
foreign
have interpersonal empathy as a behavior
as a feeling that's one whole area but
in the creation of organizations it's
almost like we have to ask not how
strongly we feel or what we feel but
whether some future person in that
organization outside of our Direct
perception cognition action Loop is
going to
have some sort of outcome because I
think it's easy just to sketch out that
you could feel really empathy empathetic
or
any emotional state and it could result
in a totally discordant State even for
somebody you care about or vice versa so
how do we not get lost with just the
introspection of the feeling of empathy
and translate that into systems whose
efficacy is equivalent to what we would
have intended
but that may not feel like empathy all
the time
yeah I mean I feel like especially for
the last couple chapters we keep running
to like a similar concept of like Earth
theme of how the individuals
wired in terms of like you know empathy
and their ability to create shared
meaning and how that bubbles up into the
rest of the organization
um and yeah like I keep feeling like
there's no way out of like hey we're
just limited as humans in our ability to
like
integrate external information and that
limits the ability of the organization
but sounds like Daniel was maybe
sounding more optimistic now like well
actually maybe you can build some maybe
there's tooling and systems you can
build that can have organizational
empathy even if the individual doesn't
have it
so that brings to like like something
that Daniel and I have talked about
before
um working on like the discussion of
memes like randomly random insertion
random plug for the Eco meme project
um but like when you're really thinking
about painting a picture to convey like
a shared meaning like we talked about
the Echolocation how the dolphin like
literally can like paint a picture like
I saw a fish over here and can like
translate like puts the picture of the
fish into the other dolphin's mind like
there's the picture of the fish right
and so like you literally can paint the
entire picture so like even if we could
do something as remarkable as that
um we convey only the semantic content
like if if you can say like
the fire hydrant is red right and like
you guys both know like can can picture
it in your mind like a red fire hydrant
right but like we don't know what
semiotic content is contained in that
message like maybe someone's colorblind
maybe they don't know if it's red or
green like they can't tell right and so
like the fire hydrants appears in this
gray thing that they think might be red
or maybe like someone has been in a
house that burned down and the fire like
the Hydra didn't work and they have this
like trauma inspiration moment right
like so so the semiotic content the
symbolism behind the message or the
picture that you painted even in a
situation where you can perfectly create
like the tooling to come to the shared
meaning or representation like you're
never gonna get the symbolism that
exists for someone else it's a highly
personal thing like we can have shared
symbolism too culturally for sure but
there's a deep level of personal
symbolism in every in every human that's
dependent on your previous life
experience I think
ah so coming back to abduction because
um we did talk about it in the section I
can't remember if it was in the last
quote or not but I just wanted to um
point out this is a recycled slide but
coming back to abduction where Bajan
talks about it is you know abductive
reasoning this is a quote from the book
abductive reasoning usually begins with
a surprising observation or experience
this is what shatters our habit and
motivates us to create a hypothesis that
might resolve the anomaly abduction is
an inferential procedure in which we
create a conjecture that if it were
if it would make the surprising anomaly
part of our normal world of our normal
understanding of the world so like this
picture is like the best way for me to
always think about abduction like you
can have a specific observation and you
can come to a general conclusion right
and then you can have deductive
reasoning where you have a general rule
but that's like leads to a specific
conclusion that's always true and then
when you have like an incomplete
observation like you can't see what's
going on you just go to the best guess
and so in business and Bhajan talks
about this again and again and again
like you have to use abductive reasoning
because we're never going to have a
complete picture of like the past and
future of the market like the whole
market right or even your target
audience so you're dealing with um the
best logical guess
um oh okay do you want to read this one
for us Tyler this is you sure uh so the
firm's generative model is the firm's
Eco Niche if uncertainty and
unpredictability dominate our worldly
perception well then this reflects the
very limitations and corrosiveness of
our models and the underlying processes
generating those models there's no
objective uncertainty there's only your
uncertainty environment is inactive each
Act opens a new Fork of multiple paths
leading to to potentially very different
outcomes realities subjective algorithm
applying an infinite number of worlds in
superposition our actions not only
create the junctures leading to
different paths but we are in control to
decide which path to take at each
structure
uh so yeah I thought this really
summarized well
um the kind of inactive cognition so
there's a proposition still in
proposition two here
um of FEG and also that was like a fun
quote because we talked about a lot on
the last stream but uh John's been using
kind of quantum uh language here and we
talked about that on the last stream of
K what exactly does does he mean there
by that
blue Daniel anything to add here
I love your Excel spreadsheet Quantum
superposition of an Excel spreadsheet
because that's great it's capturing the
late night
blurry what action selection to take
based upon the spreadsheet
great
all right so Bhajan makes this claim
also in this section he says in fact we
are challenged not to allow for the
human brain's conceptual limits to
solely determine perception and sense
making instead Outsourcing some of the
heavy information lifting to the
environment in the form of extended
cognition is the essence of optimizing
prediction error minimization the more
exponential and hence discontinuous a
market environment the more we need
self-organizing mechanisms that leverage
the world as a supervisory signal
challenging in circular causality the
very perceptual content of our
predictions and so like we've talked a
lot about like cognitive offloading or
extended cognition in terms of like
cumulative cultural Evolution not in
this bookstream per se but like over the
course of active inference like from the
very first beginning live streams we've
talked about it a lot
um because you know we now our so much
thinking is done
um externally like in it's encultured at
at some point like but with the
smartphone like we don't have to know
how to get anywhere anymore we'll just
map it so I I just I'm thinking like
that this self-organizing mechanisms
that leverage the world as a supervisory
signal challenging in circular causality
it's a very perceptual content of our
predictions like I mean I'm so amazed by
Chachi petite like I'm using it so much
um just because it's like what does
everybody know like chat GPT tells you
what everybody knows it is like the
selective synthesis of all information
right and so like if you know something
that chat gpt3 doesn't know like that's
great you can write a blog about it but
now like chat gp3 you can just write all
the blogs about every other thing
because there's just like no like it
knows everything right it's got a it's
got It's got all of the information
synthesis except like the rare pockets
of like knowledge so if this is this
this self-organizing mechanism this chat
gpt3 like a global
search synthesis
information management system I don't
know what do you guys think about that
well this is very out of my depth both
in terms of like machine learning and
active inference uh the best thing about
this last night because this is like a
huge debate right now it's like whether
tragedy T3 is actually showing like
emergent intelligence or whether it's
just like a clever clever algorithm
um and I was thinking about this too
like what are the differences between
like chat gbt3 and what I've been
learning so far about active inference
and like The crucial things it seems to
be missing is like the inactive aspect
of it like it's not really in dialogue
with this world it's like stringing
together information that's like
aesthetic right it doesn't even
incorporate new information like if you
were to ask it about the news yesterday
it couldn't it couldn't do that and it's
not making it's not taking actions in
the world and getting feedback it's just
like the static model of how the world
works
and so I don't know it feels like
fundamentally different to me and I'm
not sure what that means I'm not sure if
like something has to display active
inference to have true intelligence for
this is like a big hotly contested topic
I'm sure you guys have many live streams
about this uh but yeah Daniel blue I'm
curious what you guys think
well in the space of communication the
response it provides to you is an action
that's not moving a mechanical arm on a
table but in our internet of everything
it's not so hard to see how the digital
outputs from a generative algorithm do
translate to physical objects moving but
it may not even need to do that it can
send out messages on social media and
definitely meriting further discussion
as things will continue to develop and
gain more access to recent information
World model learning and action capacity
soon
so like I I have a a little bit of a of
a like technical response here
um
I think that the question is not about
true intelligence maybe but but the
question that I've I hear talked about a
lot is sentience right and so but like I
had read this big article about like is
that is gpt3 sentient and I think it was
like from one of the inside Google
people the one that was released and now
they're talking about it because
everyone's using it and like sentient
they just said like you know able to
think and act independently but that's
like not the definition of sentient like
I'm not sure what the definition of
sentient is but it's not like autonomous
like they're using sentient and
autonomous the same way and sentient is
like able to feel things right like so I
think like let's look it up right now
let's Define sentient for For The World
At Large what does that mean because
intelligent sentient and autonomous are
all different so hold on I'm looking on
my phone because I'm screen sharing
words words words
Alice in Wonderland people will use them
how they want but that's everything so
as sentient is able to perceive or feel
things
right and so it's gpt3 healing anything
I highly doubt it
um perceiving a lot sure
um but as to your thing about updating
Tyler like I'm sure the model will
update at some regular interval so like
just think about
um you know I mean we're not there yet
in terms of compute power but maybe in
10 years like it will be training on the
entire Wikipedia catalog every single
day so like does Wikipedia have like a
date entry for every day I think it does
right so like when you ask like what was
the news yesterday it'll know that like
that's just a matter of what's encoded
and what what's being processed through
silicone it's only time right like we're
we're way close so like it will be able
to update
um at some with some regularity like
will it update itself I don't know that
that gets into like autonomous acting
I don't know those all those things are
different I mean that reminds me those
because we've had this discussion over
the past you know 15 minutes about like
empathy and the new organizations have
empathy right and it's kind of like the
same conversation it's like gpt3 of like
okay well like maybe organizational
empathy
like it looks and just feels differently
than like individual empathy right
um and so you can imagine the same the
same thing happening in gpt3 and I don't
know what that version of empathy would
look like in gpt3 but maybe it's just
like something that we can't quite wrap
our hands around
it'll be awesome again I think a further
discussion would be very Timely
especially if for example communication
from one person's syntax could move into
a semantic space or a rhetorical space
from the Eco meme direction as blue
mentioned and then be translated back
into another semantic space for the
listener that might be changing the
amount of math detail or in a different
human natural language so there's a lot
of incredible opportunities
yeah definitely I think um you know
it'll be interesting to see to
interrogate Bhajan with such like
esoteric questions to see to interrogate
Bhajan with such like esoteric questions
and see what he thinks like does a firm
have empathy like what where did you
even get this well we got it sorry we're
off to ask
um anyway
all right so moving on uh Tyler do you
want to read this one preposition
sure so the stronger the board's dmn
Centric Duality stewardship empowering
upper echelon sustainability balance
exploitation versus exploration as well
as strategic or financial for strategic
control the stronger the firm's
orientation towards free energy surprise
minimization based self-organization the
stronger the sustainably sustainability
of successful and continuous strategic
renewal and hence the firm's prospects
for survival
foreign
so we talked about this last week a lot
I didn't put a lot of extra information
in here because we did like the
antagonistic neural
or that perspective last week
um but I did just want to include the
summary so Bajan at the end of the
chapter summarizes it by saying in
summary the board must assume the role
of sponsor or enforcer of three
categorical imperatives defining the
success and sustainability of strategic
renewal and firm survival
first foster cognitive coupling between
and within all hierarchical layers I'm
really excited to find out exactly how
to do this second Embrace environment as
action generated and socially
constructed shared meaning and shared
expectations which we've talked about a
lot today
and third the chain The Firm from
thinking in terms of antagonisms but
Embrace real-time Duality management as
a critical determinant of performance
and survival
um that's pretty much it do you guys
have any final
thoughts
the overtime period the generative AI
speculation moment
the hashtag 2023
questions that we all have
times
um so I I we talked about Quantum so I'm
leaving us with this one
um quote from this chapter because it's
just kind of like
thrown in there Bijan says classical
linear cause effect thinking is no match
for Quantum
exponentiality I wonder what it means by
Quantum exponentiality like are we again
talking about superposition are we
talking about like because that's like I
guess the many states existing at once
is that like what he means by
exponentiality what do you guys think
I think John has a poetic bent in him
not sure if we're meant to take this
fully literally
exponents are used in a lot of quantum
mechanics
readings just like any other good poem
so
we should
jump in with these kinds of questions
cool well that's next week
um so
yeah excited to wrap up this part and
just a couple more book streams left for
us uh winding down again get in touch if
you would like to participate in our
final discussion we would really welcome
any external perspectives
all right thanks see you next time